(Laughter) So I thought about it, and I kind of overcame my anxieties and my fears. I went down to the welfare office and I demanded to see the supervisor. Sure enough, he came out, and they had to let Mr. Ruiz make an application for welfare. And he got his disability for himself and his family. But that taught me a lesson. That taught me that I had a voice. Well, Mr. Ross also taught many of us many other things, including Cesar Chavez and many other volunteers. And he taught us not only that we can make demands of people, especially our public officials. And this is something we should always keep in mind: every public official -- guess what -- they work for us. Because we pay their salaries with out taxes. And they are actually our servants.
(Risas) Lo pensé bien y superé mis ansiedades y miedos. Volví a la oficina de servicios sociales y exigí ver al supervisor. En efecto, apareció, y finalmente le permitieron al Sr. Ruiz solicitar su ayuda social. Y logró ese beneficio por discapacidad para él y su familia. Pero eso me enseñó una lección. Me enseñó que tenía una voz. El Sr. Ross también nos enseñó muchas otras cosas, incluido a Cesar Chavez y muchos otros voluntarios. Nos enseñó que podemos no solo exigir a la gente, especialmente a los funcionarios públicos. Y esto es algo que siempre debemos tener presente: cada funcionario público trabaja para nosotros. Porque pagamos sus sueldos con nuestros impuestos. Y en realidad son nuestros empleados.
Some of them turn out to be leaders, but not all of them. (Laughter) Once in a while we get a leader out of there. The other thing that Mr. Ross taught us is that voting is extremely important. And not just voting, but going out there and getting other people to vote. Going door to door. Phone banking, talking to voters, because many voters have a lot of doubts and they don't know how to vote. And unfortunately, we know that in many countries people are not allowed to vote because we have voter suppression in other countries, like we do here in the United States of America. But the thing is, if we can get out there as individuals and talk to people, so we can remove their apathy and make sure that they can vote. So, I want to give you an example of a woman in our foundation, the Dolores Huerta Foundation, and just to show you that sometimes people have power, but they don't know it. But once they find it, they do miraculous things. So, Leticia Prado is an immigrant from Mexico, only has a sixth-grade education and speaks very limited English. But she was very concerned because the children at the middle school in their town called Weedpatch -- this is in California, Central Valley -- they couldn't go out and play in the schoolyard, because the air quality is so bad in the southern part of Kern County, California in our United States of America. So she and her husband went out there, and they passed a bond issue to build a brand new, state-of-the-art gymnasium for the kids at their middle school. That was a big success. Then she heard a rumor that the principal was going to end the breakfast program for the farm worker children, because the principal thought it was just too much paperwork. So, Leticia got herself elected to the school board. And they kept the breakfast program, and she got rid of the principal. (Laughter) (Applause) So there were other rumors about some corruption in the local water district. So, Leticia got herself elected to the water district. Then she looked into all of the finances of the water district and found there was 250,000 dollars missing from their bank account.
Algunos se vuelven líderes, pero no todos. (Risas) De vez en cuando surge un líder de allí. Lo otro que nos enseñó Ross es que votar es sumamente importante. Y no solo votar, sino salir a convocar a otros a que voten. Ir puerta por puerta, hacer llamadas telefónicas, hablar con los votantes, porque muchos tienen dudas y no saben cómo votar. Por desgracia, sabemos que en muchos países a la gente no se le permite votar porque hacen maniobras para impedir el voto, como aquí en los EE. UU. Pero si podemos intervenir como individuos y hablar con la gente, podemos sacarlos de su apatía y asegurarnos de que voten. Quiero darles un ejemplo de una mujer en nuestra fundación, la "Fundación Dolores Huerta", para mostrarles que a veces la gente tiene poder pero no lo sabe. Y una vez que lo encuentran, hacen cosas milagrosas. Leticia Prado es una inmigrante de México, tiene solo educación primaria y habla muy poco inglés. Pero estaba muy preocupada porque los alumnos de la secundaria en su pueblo llamado Weedpatch, en el Valle Central de California, no podían salir a jugar en el patio porque la calidad del aire es muy mala en la parte sur del condado de Kern, California, en los EE. UU. Junto a marido lograron que se apruebe una emisión de bonos para construir un nuevo y moderno gimnasio para los alumnos de la escuela. Fue un éxito enorme. Luego, Leticia escuchó el rumor de que el director iba a cancelar el programa de desayuno para los hijos de trabajadores rurales, porque pensaba que era mucho papeleo. Leticia fue electa para integrar el comité escolar. Y mantuvieron el programa de desayuno y se deshizo del director. (Risas) (Aplausos) Había otros rumores de corrupción en el servicio de provisión de agua local. Y ella fue electa para integrar la dependencia que manejaba el servicio. Luego analizó las finanzas de ese departamento y descubrió que faltaban USD 250 000 de la cuenta bancaria.
So, Leticia called in the grand jury, and several arrests have been made. And this is just an example of a woman who never went to high school, never went to college, but she found her power. And in addition, she has recruited other people in the community to also run for public office, and guess what -- they've all gotten themselves elected. So, I take that Leticia really embodies something that Coretta Scott King said. And I want to share this with you. Coretta Scott King said, "We will never have peace in the world until women take power." (Applause) Now, I have amended that statement to say that we will never have peace in the world until feminists take power. (Laughter) Because we know there is a difference, right? Not only that, but if we want to define what is a feminist -- a person who stands up for reproductive rights, for immigrants' rights, for the environment, for LGBT rights and also for labor unions and working people. (Applause) Which also means that men can also be feminists. So when we think of feminization, we should also think of how can we feminize the policies, and not only of our major countries, the wealthy countries like the United States, but all over the world, our domestic and foreign policy. And one of the things that we can do to stop wars and to have peace is to make sure that the wealthiest countries in the world also help the developing countries. Now, we did this in the past. After World War II, when Japan and Germany were devastated after the war, United States of America gave many tax dollars to those two countries, so that they can rebuild their economies and rebuild their corporations. And we can do that again. And if we can think about how we can help these other countries. And I want to give an example of issues that we are facing in the United States of America, for instance. We know that right now we have a lot of refugees from Central America that are at the border of the United States. Why do people leave their homes, their beautiful homes that we go to as tourists? Because they don't have opportunities there. And then we think, "Hm, bananas." How many jillions of bananas do we consume in the United States every single day? And throughout the world. Now, do the people in Central America get the profits from the bananas that we consume? No, they don't. The profits go to corporations from the United States of America. And we think that this is wrong. Now, if the people in Central America were to be able to get some of that money that we pay for bananas, then they wouldn't have to leave their homes. They wouldn't have to come as asylum seekers to the borders of the United States of America. And then maybe, many children would not have to be separated from their parents. Now, we know that there are countries in the world that actually have free education and have free health care for all of the people in their country. And that country is Cuba. Cuba has health care for every one of their citizens, and they have a free college education for every one of their citizens. They're 11 million citizens. Now, we think, if a poor country like Cuba can have these kind of resources, and we know that they're a poor country, then why can't some of the other wealthier countries, like the United States of America, do the same? I think that we can make that happen. (Applause) But we know it's not going to happen until we, the people of the United States of America, and people throughout the world, start making sure that they get public officials elected to their governments that really care about the constituents, they care about people, they will commit to make sure that the resources that they have are going to be used for their citizens, and not to be used for war. So, how do we make this happen? We have to get rid of the apathy, we have to get more people involved. We know that if we can't have a democracy in the United States, we can't have democracies throughout the world, unless people participate. So it is imperative that all of us get out there and we say, "Get rid of the apathy, get off of the sidewalk, come and join the march for peace and justice, let's make Coretta Scott's vision a reality, to have peace in the world." We recently had midterm elections in the United States of America. And what did we see? We saw that so many more women, young people, people of color, LGBT folks, were all elected to public office. And we know this happened -- why? Because so many women were on the march. We had the Women's March in the United States. They had the Women's Marches all over the world. And so we now see that we have this potential. We have this potential to get rid of the apathy. And if we get everyone involved, get everyone committed, then, I think, we can make Coretta Scott's vision come true. So, I want to just remind everybody, throughout the world, one of the things is, we have power, poor people have power, every citizen has power. But in order to achieve the peace that we all yearn for, then we've all got to get involved. So, what do we say? Can we do it? We say, "Yes, we can!" And in Spanish, we say, "Sí, se puede." Thank you very much. (Applause)
Leticia llamó al gran jurado y se hicieron varios arrestos. Y esto es solo un ejemplo de una mujer que nunca fue a la secundaria, nunca fue a la facultad, pero encontró su poder. Además, reclutó a otra gente de la comunidad para postularse a cargos públicos, y adivinen qué: todos fueron electos. Creo que Leticia es un ejemplo de algo que dijo Coretta Scott King, que quiero compartir con ustedes. Coretta Scott King dijo: "Nunca tendremos paz en el mundo hasta que las mujeres tomen el poder". (Aplausos) Modifiqué esa afirmación para decir que nunca tendremos paz en el mundo hasta que las feministas tomen el poder. (Risas) Porque sabemos que hay una diferencia, ¿verdad? No solo eso. Si queremos definir a una feminista, pues es una persona que defiende los derechos reproductivos, los derechos de inmigrantes, el medio ambiente, los derechos de LGBT y los sindicatos laborales y los trabajadores. (Aplausos) Lo que también significa que los hombres pueden ser feministas. Cuando pensamos en la feminización, también debemos pensar en cómo podemos feminizar las políticas, y no solo de los grandes países, los países ricos como los EE. UU., sino en todo el mundo, nuestra política interior y exterior. Y una de las cosas que podemos hacer para frenar las guerras y tener paz es asegurarnos de que los países más ricos del mundo también ayuden a los países en vías de desarrollo. Hicimos esto en el pasado. Luego de la Segunda Guerra Mundial, cuando Japón y Alemania quedaron devastadas luego de la guerra, los EE. UU. ayudaron económicamente a ambos países para que puedan reconstruir su economía y sus empresas. Y podemos volver a hacerlo. Y podemos pensar en cómo ayudar a estos países. Quiero dar un ejemplo de problemas que tenemos en los EE. UU., por caso. Sabemos que en este momento hay muchos refugiados de América Central que están en la frontera de EE. UU. ¿Por qué la gente abandona su hogar, su hermoso hogar que visitamos como turistas? Porque ahí no tienen oportunidades. Y luego pensamos "Mm... bananas". ¿Cuántos cientos de bananas consumimos en EE. UU. todos los días? Y en todo el mundo. La gente de América Central, ¿obtiene beneficios de las bananas que consumimos nosotros? Pues no. Los beneficios van a las empresas de EE. UU. Y pensamos que esto está mal. Si la gente en América Central pudiera quedarse con algo de ese dinero que pagamos por las bananas, entonces no tendrían que abandonar su hogar. No tendrían que venir como refugiados a la frontera de EE. UU. Y entonces, tal vez, muchos niños no tendrían que separarse de sus padres. Sabemos que hay países que tienen educación gratuita y asistencia médica gratuita para todos sus habitantes. Y ese país es Cuba. Cuba tiene asistencia médica para cada uno de sus ciudadanos, y también educación universitaria gratuita. Son 11 millones de ciudadanos. Entonces, si un país pobre como Cuba puede tener este tipo de recursos, y sabemos que es un país pobre, ¿por qué algunos de los países ricos, como los Estados Unidos, no pueden hacer lo mismo? Creo que podemos lograrlo. (Aplausos) Pero sabemos que no sucederá hasta que nosotros, la gente de EE. UU. y la gente de todo el mundo empiece a elegir funcionarios públicos en sus gobiernos que se preocupen por los votantes, se preocupen por la gente, que se comprometan para que los recursos disponibles sean usados para sus ciudadanos, y no para la guerra. ¿Cómo logramos esto? Tenemos que deshacernos de la apatía, tenemos que involucrar a más gente. Sabemos que si no podemos tener una democracia en los EE. UU., no podemos tener democracias en el resto del mundo, a menos que la gente participe. Es fundamental que todos participemos y digamos: "Desháganse de la apatía, salgan a la calle, vengan y súmense a la marcha por la paz y la justicia, hagamos que la visión de Coretta Scott sea realidad, la de tener paz en el mundo". Hace poco fueron las elecciones de medio término en los EE. UU. ¿Y qué vimos? Vimos que muchas más mujeres, gente joven, gente de color, LGBT, fueron elegidos para ocupar cargos públicos. Y ¿cómo sabemos que esto pasó? Porque muchas mujeres estaban en la marcha. Tuvimos la marcha de las mujeres en EE. UU., y hubo marchas de mujeres en todo el mundo. Entonces ahora vemos que tenemos este potencial. Tenemos este potencial de deshacernos de la apatía. Y si involucramos a todos, si comprometemos a todos, entonces creo que podemos hacer realidad la visión de Coretta Scott. Solo quiero recordarles a todos, en todo el mundo, que tenemos poder, que la gente pobre tiene poder, que cada ciudadano tiene poder. Pero para lograr la paz que todos anhelamos, todos tenemos que involucrarnos. ¿Qué decimos entonces? ¿Podemos hacerlo? Decimos: "¡Sí, se puede!". Y en inglés decimos: "Yes, we can!" Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)